Hey, בוקר טוב. Boker tov.
Today's דף daf is דף ז, daf zayin, we pick up at
the bottom of ו עמוד ב, vav amud bet,
and we are a little bit of a digression, we're talking about
from where in practical current times, current in the גמרא, Gemara, the
whole statement of the שליח shaliach of בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם bifnei
nichtav uvifnei nechtam has to be said, and the גמרא Gemara recently
sort of said that like you reevaluate within מדינת הים, medinat hayam,
you know, even if it's like from one neighbor to the next
or within a neighborhood or whatever, if it's highly transient or people
don't recognize the signatures you would have to say, which leads תוספות
Tosafot and the ראשונים rishonim to say that it seems like these
are one of these תקנות takanot which don't remain sort of fixed,
but that you always have to but that you reassess based on
the circumstances. The one interesting question that רמב"ן Ramban raises, I didn't
mention yesterday, is that the גמרא Gemara is reassessing in terms of
מדינת הים. medinat hayam. The רמב"ן Ramban raises the question about whether
in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, if the situation had become what it
did in the time of the ראשונים, rishonim, that there is not
as much תורה Torah knowledge in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, that there's
not as much travel, that there's all these problems with, you know,
could you ever imagine a case where in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
you'd have to say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם bifnei nichtav uvifnei nechtam
or do we say no, no, no, ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is
like always exempt? The questions about where you have to say it
is only questions in חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz. So that's an issue
that the רמב"ן Ramban raises. Anyway, that's the issue. And then the
גמרא Gemara just gave the special status to בבל, Bavel, that within
בבל Bavel it's like within ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and you don't
have to say because there's travel and knowledge of לשמה. lishmah. And
then it said when you go from בבל Bavel to ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael or vice versa,
according to רבי אביתר, Rabbi Avyasar, who was it, where was it,
רבי אביתר, Rabbi Avyasar,
he said that you do not have to say, which led the
גמרא Gemara challenging the statements of רבי אביתר, Rabbi Avyasar, who says
that he's somebody you can rely on. He wrote this whole blistering
critique of the practice in בבל Bavel to send their to leave
their homes and their wives and their children and go study in
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. He wrote this whole critique of this but
he wrote it quoting a פסוק pasuk and he didn't underline the
פסוק. pasuk. So this is a way of like undermining his authority.
He doesn't really know what he's talking about. He didn't know that
you're supposed to score a פסוק pasuk when you write it when
you write it. So the גמרא Gemara says, you know, that's not
necessarily something that everybody has to know. Okay and now with that
sort of as the background we're going to get to other statements
about רבי אביתר Rabbi Avyasar and about writing פסוקים psukim and scoring
them and so on. So, by the way, that just struck me
that that's partly where we get the word to underscore, right, just
to score under. And in the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, I don't
know what happened to my markers, but they put the scoring above,
right? The scoring is not an ink line, it's an indented line
like, you know, but if you ever look at a ספר תורה,
Sefer Torah, you know, you have they have these lines which are
like, you know, scratched in, indented in, but they're actually above, right?
So the scoring sort of is like this, you know, so scoring
appears, the letters are sort of suspended from the scoring. Okay, but
anyway, but that's probably where you get the word underscore from is
to put the scoring underneath. Anyway, okay back to the גמרא. Gemara.
So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, ועוד, v'od, two lines down in the wide lines in ו
עמוד ב. vav amud bet. ועוד v'od says the גמרא, Gemara, in
addition, to show you that just, you know, not only can you
not dismiss רבי אביתר Rabbi Avyasar just because he didn't know this
הלכה halacha about scoring when you're quoting פסוקים, psukim, but ועוד הא
רבי אביתר הוא דאסיק מריה דייקיה. v'od ha Rabbi Avyasar hu d'asik
marei deikyei. רבי אביתר, Rabbi Avyasar, his master, meaning God,
agreed with what he was saying. He was מכוון mechaven to something
that the, you know, that only he could know if he had
special knowledge. How do you know? דכתיב, d'ichtiv, a verse says,
ותזנה עליו פילגשו. vatizneh alav pilegsho. Interesting bringing this in especially in
the context of מסכת גיטין. Masechet Gittin.
His concubine committed adultery against him. This is the story about פילגש
בגבעה. pilegeish b'Givah. And then, you know, and then he drove her
from his house and then she was, you know, raped by all
these people and that led to the whole wars around פילגש בגבעה.
pilegeish b'Givah. So the גמרא Gemara says what does that mean, ותזנה
עליו? vatizneh alav? So רבי אביתר אמר זבוב מצא לה, Rabbi Avyasar
amar zvev matza lah, that it does not literally mean she committed
adultery, it means that he found a fly, we'll see where this
is from, a fly at least according to one גמרא Gemara in
the food from the word מזונות mezonot maybe. It's what תוספות Tosafot
says. ורבי יונתן אמר נימא מצא לה. v'Rabbi Yonatan amar nima matza
lah. He found a strand of hair. ואשכחיה
רבי אביתר לאליהו. v'ashkachei Rabbi Avyasar l'Eliyahu. רבי אביתר Rabbi Avyasar found
אליהו. Eliyahu. אמר ליה מאי קעביד הקדוש ברוך הוא? amar lei mai
ka avid Hakadosh Baruch Hu? What's God doing right now? אמר ליה
עסיק בפילגש בגבעה. amar lei asik b'pilegeish b'Givah. He's studying the סוגיא
sugya of פילגש בגבעה. pilegeish b'Givah. ומאי קאמר? u'mai ka amar? What's
he saying?
אמר ליה אמר ליה אביתר בני כך הוא אומר. amar lei Avyasar
bni kach hu omer. Well, let's see what happened in the פילגש
בגבעה pilegeish b'Givah story. אביתר Avyasar my son says this is what
happened. יונתן בני כך הוא אומר. Yonatan bni kach hu omer. אמר
ליה, amar lei, so רבי אביתר, Rabbi Avyasar, you should feel good,
look at this, God's talking about what you said. But no, he
said back to אליהו, Eliyahu, חס ושלום! chas v'shalom! ומי קא ספקא
קמיה שמיא? u'mi ka sfeka kamei shamaya? God forbid, how could God
have to, you know, be saying what we said? Doesn't God know?
אמר ליה אלו ואלו דברי אלוהים חיים. amar lei eilu v'eilu divrei
Elokim chayim. These and these are the words of the living God.
Both statements are correct. הין זבוב מצא ולא הקפיד. Hein z'vuv matza
v'lo hikpid. He found the fly,
the פילגש's pilegesh master, and did not get angry. נימא מצא והקפיד,
Nima matza v'hikpid, but he found the string of hair and he
got angry. So even though ultimately רב יונתן Rav Yonatan was more
right than רב אביתר, Rav Evyatar, but רב אביתר Rav Evyatar was
still מכוון m'chuven to something that would be impossible to really know
about and God was interested in what רב אביתר Rav Evyatar said,
so you see that רב אביתר Rav Evyatar you cannot just dismiss
him. Not that I don't think any of that gives him any
halachic weight, but from the attempt to dismiss him, this is being
given as counterproof not to dismiss him. And now the גמרא Gemara
gets a little bit more explicit about this.
Yeah, he could easily have contaminated the soup after she served it,
where a hair would have been from the pot or from her
serving.
Oh, I see.
It makes sense
that he was מקפיד makpid more on the hair. Well, that's what
the גמרא's Gemara going to get to. Let's see why he got
more upset about one than the other.
So אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, so נימא מצא והקפיד. Nima
matza v'hikpid. אמר רב יהודה זבוב בקערה ונימא באותו מקום. Amar Rav
Yehuda z'vuv b'ke'ara v'nima b'oto makom. So now we're going to get
a little more graphic. The problem was that the fly was in
the food, but the hair was in that place because based on
a certain גמרא Gemara it seems that they had the practice to
shave their pubic area and he was upset that there was still
hair there. Maybe they thought that that would be some type of
a danger to or injury of their genitals. So that's why he
got so upset.
נימא מצא והקפיד. Nima matza v'hikpid. Where were we? באותו מקום. B'oto
makom. זבוב מיאוסא. Z'vuv me'usa. זבוב Z'vuv is just disgusting, but נימא
סכנתא, Nima sakanta, but the hair that was an actual danger. איכא
דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some say אידי ואידי בקערה. Idy v'idy b'ke'ara. They
were both found in the soup. זבוב
אונסא. Z'vuv unsa. זבוב Z'vuv is an אונס. ones. What can you
do? A fly flies in. You can't stop flies from flying in.
נימא פשיעותא, Nima pshiyuta, but the hair that was just negligence. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. ונימא. V'nima. I'm sorry.
זבוב אונסא. Z'vuv unsa. ונימא סכנתא. V'nima sakanta. איכא דאמרי אידי ואידי
בקערה. Ika d'amri idy v'idy b'ke'ara. I just said that. אמר רב
חסדא. Amar Rav Chisda.
So that's a little bizarre. I was trying to figure out in
addition to how the גמרא's Gemara trying to defend רב אביתר. Rav
Evyatar. Was this discussion about how
out of proportion the husband could get and he drove his
פילגש pilegesh out. It is interesting from the very beginning of גיטין,
Gittin, nobody, the husband is not looking good for the whole discussion
from the outset is that maybe אסי בעל מערער, asi ba'al me'ar'er,
the husband is going to come and make an object and trump
up some claim in order to make the wife's life difficult on
her. We're trying to protect the woman's interests and so on. And
here we have this story about this husband that gets angry over
a hair or a fly and drives his not exactly wife, but
nevertheless, concubine from the house.
He wanted her to be, he wants her back?
What? He wanted,
by negating the גט get they would be married again.
Maybe, but maybe it also sounds like one of those stories where
he's not going to get her back but he's just going to
make her life impossible. If I can't have you, nobody can type
of a thing. If he's raising this claim, the גמרא Gemara never
suggests that actually he would succeed. He'd just succeed enough to make
her. I don't think that seems like that that was a reasonable
outcome when he was going to be מערער. me'ar'er. But anyway, maybe
that's what he thinks, maybe you're right. Okay, אמר רב חסדא. Amar
Rav Chisda. לעולם אל יטיל אדם אימה יתירה בתוך ביתו. Le'olam al
yatil adam eimah yeteirah b'toch beito. A person should never create undue
fear in his household. Meaning the man should not create fear on
his wife and kids. שהרי פילגש בגבעה הטיל עליה בעלה אימה יתירה.
Sheharei pilegesh b'givah hitil aleha ba'alah eimah yeteirah. He created great fear
on her because she basically ran away. And what happened as a
result? והפילה כמה רבבות
מישראל V'hipila kama rivavot mi'Yisrael and caused many myriads of people to
die amongst the Jewish people because of the war that ensued. אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב כל המטיל אימה יתירה בתוך ביתו סוף הוא
בא לידי שלוש עבירות. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav kol hamatil eimah
yeteirah b'toch beito sof hu ba lidei shalosh aveirot. Anybody who creates
undue fear in their household ends up with three sins. גילוי עריות
ושפיכות
דמים וחילול שבת. Gilui arayot v'shfichut damim v'chilul Shabbat.
How do you get those three? So רש"י Rashi says גילוי עריות
כשמגיע זמן טבילתה בעת צנה והיא יראה לומר לא טבלתי ומשמשתו נידה.
Gilui arayot k'shemagia z'man tvilatah b'eit tzina v'hi yarei lomar lo tavalti
u'm'shameshto niddah.
So she's afraid to say I didn't go to the מקוה mikvah
because the water's so freezing cold. We don't appreciate how amazing those
stories of history were. Women having to go down into these deep
wells in the middle of the night in all darkness to go
to the מקוה mikvah and freezing cold and so on. So you
don't want to go, but you don't want to say you didn't
go, so that's גילוי עריות. gilui arayot. ושפיכות דמים, V'shfichut damim, רש"י
Rashi says דהכא, d'hacha, like here, what it ultimately led, I mean
to driving her from the house and her being afraid and running
and then it led to this whole war. או פעמים שבורחת מפניו.
O p'amim sheborachat mipanav. She's running away from him because she's afraid
of him. ונופלת באחת הפחתים או בגשר. V'nofelet b'achat hap'chatim o b'gesher.
And some accident occurs and she dies as a result. ומה חילול
שבת? U'ma chilul Shabbat? פעמים שמדלקת הנר ומבשלת משחשיכה מפני אימתו. P'amim
shemadleket haner u'm'vashelet mishechasheicha mipnei eimato.
She didn't light the candles and she didn't cook the meals and
she's afraid what he's going to do. והוא אינו יודע. V'hu eino
yodeia. So it's actually her חילול שבת chilul Shabbat but he's ultimately
to blame. Yes, David.
Oh, that's interesting.
I can't figure out
the חילול, chillul, well, some have, if you look at תוספות, Tosafos,
some have שלוש עבירות. shalosh aveiros. תוספות Tosafos says בסדר עולם אמר
דאותו יום דפילגש בגבעה שבת היה, BeSeder Olam amar de'oso yom de'Pilegesh
BeGivah Shabbat hayah,
so that would make חילול שבת chillul Shabbat connected to the day
to פילגש בגבעה. Pilegesh BeGivah. ורבינו חננאל כתב ג' עבירות גילוי עריות
ושפיכות דמים וחילול השם. v'Rabbeinu Chananel kasav gimmel aveiros gillui arayos u'shefichus
damim v'chillul Hashem. Okay,
and instead of חילול שבת, chillul Shabbat, חילול השם, chillul Hashem, you
could see how those are almost the same word. Okay, וג' היו
בפילגש בגבעה, v'gimmel hayu bi'Pilegesh BeGivah, and all those three were relevant
to the פילגש בגבעה Pilegesh BeGivah story. Okay.
והוא אינו יודע
v'hu
eino
yodeya because it's his חילול שבת chillul Shabbat because he eats the
food that was cooked on שבת.
Shabbos. Oh, you think that's why? That he's...
והוא בא לידי
עבירה.
v'hu ba
lidei aveirah.
I see. You don't just mean that it's that he's caused it
but that somehow he's... גילוי עריות. gillui arayos. Maybe. Right, right, right.
That I got. Right, right, right. That's interesting. Maybe I should be
right about that. Okay. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן.
Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan. So now, so again,
very interesting right in this whole מסכת גיטין Masechet Gittin to open
up with this אגדתא Agaddata about, you
know, ways the husband can like act in the home that creates
this terrible situation circumstance. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן
הא דאמרי רבנן. Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan ha
de'amri Rabbanan. That's what the Rabbis say. שלשה דברים צריך אדם לומר
בתוך ביתו ערב שבת עם חשכה. Sheloshah devarim tzarich adam lomar besoch
beiso erev Shabbat im chashechah.
A man has to say three things in his house, meaning to
his wife, right before it gets dark on שבת. Shabbos. עשרתם, ערבתם,
הדליקו את הנר. Issartem, eiravtem, hadliku es haner.
Have you taken מעשר? maaser? Have you done עירוב חצרות eiruv chatzeiros
or עירוב תחומין? eiruv techumin? מחלוקת רש"י תוספות. machlokes Rashi Tosfos. Light
the candles. So those three things, צריך למימרינהו בניחוסא. tzarich lemimreinhu benichusa.
You have to say them pleasantly. Don't be angry. Have you done
it? Have you done it yet? Right? Don't go yelling, right? Just
talk nicely. כי היכי דליקבלו מיניה, ki heichi delikablu minei, so that
people should listen to you and act accordingly and not like either,
you know, and and just, you know, be a מענטש mensch basically.
Before we were sort of saying that they'll do things out of
fear that they wouldn't want to have done. Here maybe it's the
opposite. They won't do it if you yell at them. But either
way, you know, try to get along well, you know, with people
in your household, your wife and so on, talk nicely. אמר אביי
אנא לא שמיענא להא דרבה בר בר חנה. Amar Abaye ana lo
shmiyena le'ha de'Rabbah bar bar Chana. I didn't hear him. I never
heard this statement. וקיימתיה מסברא, v'kiyamtiyah misvara, but I figured that one
out on my own. Okay. Which is good. Alright. Anyway, אמר רבי
אבהו. Amar Rabbi Abbahu. לעולם. Le'olam. Now we're going to continue with
this. אל יטיל אדם אימה יתירה בתוך ביתו. Al yatil adam eimah
yeseirah besoch beiso. Do not create undue fear in your house, extra
fear. שהרי אדם גדול הטילו אימה יתירה בתוך ביתו והאכילוהו דבר גדול.
Sheharei adam gadol hitilu eimah yeseirah besoch beiso v'he'echiluhu davar gadol. So
the great... so there's a certain person who had everybody in the
house afraid of him and they almost fed him a big טרפה
treif thing. So what was that? דבר גדול. davar gadol. ומנו? u'manu?
Who is it? רבי חנינא בן גמליאל. Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel. And
it was רבי חנינא בן גמליאל. Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel. הס אאכילוהו
דבר גדול? Has a'achiluhu davar gadol? Is it really possible they fed
him such a טרפה treif thing? השתא בבהמתן של צדיקים אין הקדוש
ברוך הוא מביא תקלה על ידם. Hashta be'behemtan shel tzadikkim ein HaKadosh
Baruch Hu meivi takalah al yadam. If the animals of the righteous
God doesn't cause them to accidentally do something wrong, the donkey of
פנחס בן יאיר Pinchas ben Yair was saved from even eating, like,
you know, stuff that wasn't taken תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'maasros from. בצדיקים
עצמם לא כל שכן? be'tzadikkim atzmam lo kol shekein? How much more
so would God not let the righteous accidentally do such a big
sin? אלא בקשו להאכילו דבר גדול. Ela bikshu le'ha'achilo davar gadol. They
wanted to feed him some big טרפה treif thing. ומה ניהו? u'ma
nihu? What was it? אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. So basically
as רש"י Rashi said, like they didn't have the... some like part
of the animal got lost or whatever, they didn't שחט shecht it,
they had to rip off a limb from another live animal because
it was time for the meal. Anyway, and they were about to
do... feed this to him because he had them so afraid of
what would happen if they had actually done something wrong. תוספות Tosafos
has a famous תוספות Tosafos or whatever, regular repeat תוספות Tosafos says...
if you look at תוספות השתא בבהמתן של צדיקים. Tosfos Hashta be'behemtan
shel tzadikkim. תוספות Tosfos says אומר הר"י דלא פלגא לגבי מידי דאכילה.
omer ha'Ri de'lo palga legabi midi de'achilah. It's not like צדיקים tzadikkim
can't accidentally do sins. But this is a particular approach that the
חכמים Chachamim have about food, that the idea of eating טרפה treif
food is seen like as something terribly disastrous. דגנאי הוא לצדיק שיאכל
דבר איסור. de'gnai hu le'tzaddik she'yochal davar issur. It would be completely...
it would be a shame, like or you know, embarrassment, the... a
disgrace to eat something that would be forbidden actually enter into your
body. Okay, and therefore the גמרא Gemara says in other cases in
the גמרא Gemara where people did wrong things and the גמרא Gemara
didn't say, oh, how could God have let a mistake happen to
them, some sin happen to them. It's specifically an issue about eating
טרפה treif food. I mean there's interesting things that get associated with
eating טרפה treif food more than other problems. Like for example, the
idea that like feeding infants non-כשר kosher food, which obviously below the
age of חינוך, chinuch, but somehow it's seen as something that like
impurifies the body. I'm actually right now just working on a whole
topic.
There's also משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu in the...
right, משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu refused to nurse. There's a whole interesting
thing about not doing business in non-כשר kosher food.
And and you know and there's some תשובות teshuvos because obviously in
the Middle Ages whatever Jews had to make a living, so sometimes
they would have to do business in non-כשר kosher food and there's
attempts to try to find היתר hetter for them and every now
and then they could find a היתר hetter but not so often.
And it struck me the irony that of course a major area
of commerce for Jews in the Middle Ages was... עבודה זרה?
avodah zarah? Interest? עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. Interest? Well yes, that's true, but that wasn't my point.
My point was exactly dealing with dealing with the ritual objects of
of of other faiths, like buying and selling ritual objects for like,
you know, for Christians and the priests and the goblets and the
chalices and the whole thing. And that they found a lot of
היתר. hetter. it was very rare that they found a היתר heter
for. Yeah, but you know the תוספות Tosafot is just for a
צורך, tzorech, it's for a צורך. tzorech. Right,
I understand that. I'm just broadening it around the extra concern that
develops nonetheless, even if the תוספות Tosafot is so...
Right, right, that is correct. But there other things that are like,
you know, anyway,
but yes. Okay, okay, so, what?
I don't tell a joke.
Oh, no, no, I don't have time for that joke. Okay, that
you'd like to, you need to like set up or whatever. Anyway,
so,
okay, don't get me started with that. Okay, אלא, Ella, the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Okay, so שלח ליה מר עוקבא לרבי אלעזר,
Shelach lei Mar Ukva le-Rabbi Elazar, בני אדם העומדים עלי. Bnei Adam
ha-omedim alai. Now, so that was the development of the אימה יתירה
בתוך ביתו, Eimah yeteirah betoch beito, which again one wonders again has
interest in the context here, especially in מסכת גיטין, Masechet Gittin, which
is about like the man's unilateral power right within the גט get
and to give a גט get to his wife against her will
and so on, right? So it's interesting that critique at the beginning
about the אימה יתירה בתוך ביתו Eimah yeteirah betoch beito and the
you know the way the control over the wife and so on.
So anyway, now the גמרא Gemara developing the whole idea of the
writing of the פסוק pasuk and doing the שירטוט, sirtut, the scoring
when you quote a פסוק pasuk is now going to have some
דרשות drashot about that. So we have a little אגדתא Aggadeta today.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. שלח ליה מר עוקבא לרבי
אלעזר. Shelach lei Mar Ukva le-Rabbi Elazar.
So מר עוקבא Mar Ukva sent to רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. בני
אדם העומדים עלי, Bnei Adam ha-omedim alai, there are people that are
attacking me like, you know, criticizing me, giving me a hard time,
ובידי למוסרם למלכות, u-veyadi le-mosram la-malchut, but and I can actually hand
them over to the government because I have some information about them.
So מהו, mahu, am I allowed to do them? So, well exactly,
the מסירה mesirah issue. מהו, mahu, so what can I do? But
here it's like protecting myself. So שירטף וכתב ליה, Sirtef ve-chatav lei,
so this is why it's being quoted, he scored the parchment and
he wrote the following פסוק pasuk as an answer to the question:
אמרתי אשמרה דרכי מחטוא בלשוני, Amarti eshmerah derachai me-chato bi-leshoni, I said
I would guard my path from sinning with my tongue, אשמרה לפי
מחסום בעוד רשע לנגדי, Eshmerah le-fi machsom be-od rasha le-negdi, I will
watch my mouth keeping it muzzled while the wicked is against me.
אף על פי שרשע לנגדי, Af al pi she-rasha le-negdi, even though
the wicked person stands up against you against me whatever, אשמרה לפי
מחסום, Eshmerah le-fi machsom, keep your watch your mouth, keep it muzzled,
don't don't you know talk out against him. שלח ליה, Shelach lei,
he sent back to him, קא מצערי לי טובא, Ka mizaari li
tuva, but he's causing me tremendous anguish, ולא מצינא דאיקום בהו, ve-la
mitzina de-eikum behu, I have no other way that I can protect
myself against him. שלח ליה, Shelach lei, he sent back to him,
דום לה' והתחולל לו, Dom l'Hashem ve-hitcholel lo, be silent to God
and long for him.
דום לה', Dom l'Hashem,
right if שירטף וכתב ליה, sirtef ve-chatav lei, דום לה', Dom l'Hashem,
be silent to God והוא יפילם לך חללים חללים, ve-hu yapilem lecha
chalalim chalalim, nevertheless don't you speak out against him, be quiet, God
will take care of him, God will cause him to fall. השכם
והערב עליהם לבית המדרש, Hashkem ve-haarev aleihem le-veit ha-midrash, and now here's
at least if you want to do something, here's what you should
do: so get up and stay late to the
בית המדרש, Beit ha-Midrash, ואנן כלין מאליהן, ve-inan kalin me-aleihen, and they'll
disappear on their own. So maybe
the idea of דום dom is learned as sort of I'm not
the connected to תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah I'm not exactly sure how.
Anyway, הדבר יצא מפי רבי אלעזר, Ha-davar yatza mi-pi Rabbi Elazar, as
soon as רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar said this, ונתנוהו לגניבא בקולר, ve-natnuhu
le-Gneiva be-kolar, גניבא Gneiva who was a mean guy, the word גניבא
Gneiva also is pretty much of an indicator. Anyway, he was put
in chains. He was the parallel, yeah what what what? המן? Haman?
אמן? Amen? הדבר יצא, Ha-davar yatza, yeah, המן חפו, Haman chapu, right
and this
is the מלכות, malchut, אחשורוש? Achashverosh? Right,
right,
right, that's I mean obviously the הדבר יצא ha-davar yatza you realize
that, but maybe but the greater parallel too is you could be
right about that. Anyway, yeah, yeah, I got it, I got it.
So anyway it's a good point. So God right, so they put
גניבא Gneiva into chains. Okay, שלח ליה למר עוקבא, Shelach lei le-Mar
Ukva, so that was מר עוקבא Mar Ukva who was sending the
question
to רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. Now מר עוקבא Mar Ukva had the
following question sent to him. זימרא מנלן דאסיר, Zimra minalan de-assir, so
this ties into the end of מסכת סוטה. Masechet Sotah. How do
we know we're not allowed to play music? שירטף וכתב להו, Sirtef
ve-chatav le-hu, he scratched on a whatever, he scored on a parchment
and he wrote them: אל תשמח ישראל אל גיל בעמים, Al tismach
Yisrael el gil ba-amim,
Israel you should not rejoice in the rejoicing of nations, certainly after
the חורבן הבית. Churban ha-Bayit.
That was written while the first temple was still standing.
This is
yeah, that's true, that was תרי דהושע trei de-Hoshea correct. ולישלח ליה
מהכא, ve-lishlach lei me-hacha, why didn't he send the following verse: בשיר
לא ישתו יין, Be-shir lo yishtu yayin, in song they shall not
drink wine, ימר שכר לשותיו, yemar shechar le-shotav, the wine will become
bitter to those who drink it. אי מההוא, Ei me-hahu, if it
was with that, הוה אמינא הני מילי זימרא דמנא, hava amina hani
mili zimra de-mana, that's only for playing a musical instrument, אבל דפומא
שרי, aval de-puma shari, but just to sing with your you know
vocal is not a problem, קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that
it's not. Now with this point that this is really... קא משמע
לן, ka mashma lan, excuse me, that's not limited to that, that
it's a problem even if it's just vocal. So is this really
true? So take a look at תוספות. Tosafot. By the way, the
previous תוספות Tosafot was השכם והערב עליהם, hashkem ve-haarev aleihem, דרש דום
כמו דמדומי חמה, darsh dom kemo dimdumei chamah, or
you know early in the morning or whatever, so that's the
early and late in the בית המדרש. Beit ha-Midrash. Now זימרא מנלן
דאסיר, zimra minalan de-assir, תוספות Tosafot says: פירש בקונטרס לשור בבית המשתאות,
peresh be-kuntres lashor be-veit ha-mishta'ot,
we're specifically talking about singing in like the drinking houses. וכן משמע
מדקאמר ולישלח ליה מהכא בשיר לא ישתו יין, ve-chen mashma mi-de-ka'amar ve-lishlach
lei me-hacha be-shir lo yishtu yayin, with the emphasis on wine. ובפרק
בתרא דסוטה תנן, u-ve-perek batra de-Sotah tnan, משבטלה סנהדרין בטל השיר בבית
המשתאות. mishe-batla Sanhedrin batel ha-shir be-veit ha-mishta'ot.
Okay remember that, singing in the drinking houses, שנאמר בשיר לא ישתו
יין, shenemar bishir lo yishtu yayin, וראוי להחמיר וכיוצא. veraui lehachmir vekayotze.
והא דאיתא בירושלמי דהוי קאי ודמיך בזימרא veha de'ita biyerushalmi dehavei kaei
udamich bezimra שמתענג ביותר. shemit'aneg beyoter. So it's
not just in the drinking houses, in the הירושלמי Yerushalmi it speaks
about rising up and going to sleep to music, okay. שיר של
מצוה שרי, shir shel mitzvah shari,
but when it's a מצוה mitzvah related like בשעת חופה bish'at chuppah
שעושים לשמח חתן וכלה she'osim lesame'ach chassan vechallah or saying זמירות, zemiros,
so there's a whole bunch of literature. It also ties into issues
that came up at the end of סוטה, Sotah, right, about a
famous bit in the גמרא Gemara that's against singing and then, you
know, but then whole discussions in various ראשונים ופוסקים Rishonim uposkim about
where is it allowed, where's it not allowed, how מחמיר machmir are
we on that or not. Okay. Is it only live music, nowadays
how we have recorded music, very different story. Okay. Now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. אמר ליה רב הונא בר רב נתן לרב
אשי. Amar lei Rav Huna bar Rav Natan leRav Ashi. So רב
הונא בר רב נתן Rav Huna bar Rav Natan said to רב
אשי: Rav Ashi: מאי דכתיב, mai dichtsiv, what's meant by the פסוק
pasuk in יהושע: Yehoshua: קינה ודימונה ועדעדה? Kinah veDimonah ve'Ad'adah?
So these are names, name places. אמר ליה, Amar lei, מתסא דארץ
ישראל קחשיב. matasa de'eretz yisrael kachashiv. What are you brought? It's names
of cities in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Might also be tying into
the theme of this מסכת masechet which has all the, or this
פרק perek has all the cities in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, אטו אנא לא ידענא דמתסא דארץ ישראל קחשיב? atu
ana lo yadana dematasa de'eretz yisrael kachashiv? What? I didn't realize? You
think I didn't realize that those were names of cities in ארץ
ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? I wanted you to say something interesting about it.
אלא רב גביהא מארגיזא הוה אמר בה טעמא. Ella Rav Geviha me'argiza
hava amar bah ta'ama. But רב גביהא מארגיזא, Rav Geviha me'argiza, he
said a nice דרשה drasha on this. What דרשה drasha did he
say? כל שיש לו קינה על חבירו, kol sheyesh lo kinah al
chaveiro, anybody that has any jealousy or any complaint against his friend,
ודומה vedomeh and is silent—קינה ודימונה Kinah veDimonah and is silent, so
ודומה, vedomeh, שוכני עדי עד, shochney adei ad, then the next word
is
what's the word? עדעדה. Ad'adah. So שוכני עדי עד, shochney adei ad,
the one who dwells for, you know, for eternity, עושה
לו דין, oseh lo din, will do justice for him, which... which
goes back to that story with גיניבא. Gineiva. No, but well, maybe,
but with גיניבא. Gineiva. You know,
he's causing you trouble, just pray to God, God will take care
of him. אמר ליה, Amar lei, אלא מעתה, ella me'atah, if you're
going to start דרשנינג darshaning the names of the cities, let's see
if you can do this for the rest of the פסוק. pasuk.
Okay, let's see how far you can keep this going, how long
you can keep this go. צקלג ומדמנה וסנסנה. Tziklag veMadmannah veSansannah.
הכא נמי, Hacha nami,
so here too you gotta דרשה drasha for this one? אמר ליה,
Amar lei, אי הוי רב גביהא מבי כתיל הכא הוה אמר בה
טעמא. ei havei Rav Geviha mibei Kasil hacha hava amar bah ta'ama.
You know what, if רב גביהא Rav Geviha was here, he would
have a דרשה drasha for that. Okay, so רב אחא מבי
חוזאה Rav Acha mibei Choza'ah actually he said, oh, you want a
דרשה drasha for that פסוק, pasuk, I got one for you. כל
מי שיש לו צעקת לגימא על חבירו. kol mi sheyesh lo tza'akas
legima al chaveiro. So צקלג, Tziklag,
anybody who has a crying out of לגימא legima is like food,
you know, because basically somebody else is causing him even to compromise
to lose his livelihood. He doesn't even be able to put food
on the table and he has a right to cry out about
that and he has a complaint against his friend. ודומה, vedomeh, that's
ומדמנה veMadmannah I think. Anyway, and is silent and does not attack
him. שוכן בסנה—סנסנה—the one who dwells in the, you know, in the
bush,
עושה לו דין, oseh lo din, will come to defend him. Okay.
אמר ליה ריש גלותא לרב הונא. Amar lei Reish Galusa leRav Huna.
So we're jumping back and forth. So we jumped back to the
whole thing about how, you know, don't attack somebody even if they're
giving you a hard time. Don't hand them over to the government,
God will take care of him. Now we're jumping back to the
whole issue about the playing music. So אמר ליה ריש גלותא לרב
הונא, Amar lei Reish Galusa leRav Huna, כלילא מנלן דאסור? kelila minalan
de'assur? How do we know that the crown that was worn, you
know, by the חתן chassan at, you know, again this is the
end of מסכת סוטה. masechet Sotah. It's very interesting, you know, because
maybe our גמרא Gemara felt bad. Normal גמרא Gemara starts by saying:
what does this מסכת masechet doing, why did it follow the previous
מסכת? masechet? But our גמרא Gemara נעבך, nebech, the very first line
it got right into the real meat of the matter, like why
are you saying פניך כפניך? panecha kepanecha? So now we're doing some
tie-ins to the end of מסכת סוטה. masechet Sotah. So, you know,
first we did with the playing of the music, which it said
they didn't do, you know, at the time of the חורבן הבית.
churban habayis. And now we're doing with the wearing of the crowns,
you know, that the bridegrooms would wear, right? What?
They already had עטרת זהב ateres zahav for the כלות. kallos. Right,
exactly.
But sounds like we're going to start with the חתן chassan himself.
So let's take a look. Okay.
So it says like this, so כלילא מנלן דאסור? kelila minalan de'assur?
How do you know that that's forbidden? אמר ליה מדרבנן. Amar lei
miderabbanan. It's דרבנן. rabbinic. And and he quotes actually explicitly the משנה
mishnah of סוטה: Sotah: בפולמוס של אספסיינוס, bepulmus shel Aspasyanos,
in the wars of Vespasian, גזרו על עטרות חתנים ועל האירוס. gazru
al ataros chassanim ve'al ha'irus. They made a גזירה gezeirah not to
wear these crowns of the grooms and the drums. אדהכי קם רב
הונא לאפנויי. adeihachi kam Rav Huna le'afnu'ei. So that's what the ריש
גלותא Reish Galusa asked רב הונא. Rav Huna. Then רב הונא Rav
Huna had to go take a leave and go to the bathroom.
אמר ליה רב חסדא. Amar lei Rav Chisda. So רב חסדא Rav
Chisda was left alone with the ריש גלותא. Reish Galusa. He says:
קרא כתיב. kra ksiv. You know, I can actually show you that
it's a פסוק. pasuk. כה אמר ה' אלקים, koh amar Hashem Elokim,
so says Hashem God: הסיר המצנפת והרים העטרה. hasir hamitznefes veharim ha'atarah.
Remove the,
the the hat, the mitre,
and lift off the crown. זאת לא זאת. zos lo zos. This
not even this. השפלה הגבה והגבוה השפיל. hashpalah hagbeih vehagavo'ah hashpil. The
low level rise up and the high one bring down. וכי מה
ענין מצנפת אצל עטרה? vechi mah inyan mitznefes eitzel atarah? What is
what is the connection between the mitre and the crown? by a
crown? אלא לומר לך, ella lomar lach,
to tell you, בזמן שמצנפת בראש כהן גדול, bizman shemitznefet berosh kohen
gadol, when the מצנפת mitznefet was at the top on the head
of the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, when there was a בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, עטרה בראש כל אדם, atarah berosh kol adam, then you're
allowed to wear crowns, these crowns that they would wear when they
would get married. נסתלקה מצנפת מראש כהן גדול, nistalka mitznefet merosh kohen
gadol, but once it was no longer on the head of the
כהן גדול, kohen gadol, once there’s a חורבן הבית, Churban Habayis, נסתלקה
עטרה מראש כל אדם, nistalka atarah merosh kol adam,
then nobody else is able to wear crowns when they get married.
אדהכי, adeihachi, so while he was giving this דרשה, drasha, אתא רב
הונא. ata Rav Huna. רב הונא Rav Huna came back. אשכחינהו דהוו
יתבי, ashkechinahu d’havu yasvi, and he saw that they were sitting and
they were talking in this פסוק pasuk and he was saying, "Hey,
what are you throwing on me?" He said, "Well, I told him
it was a פסוק." pasuk. אמר ליה, amar lei, so רב הונא
Rav Huna said, "האלוהים, ha'elohim, as God, by God, מדרבנן, miderabbanan, it’s
rabbinic, it’s not a פסוק. pasuk. Give me a break, this is
a דרבנן derabbanan גזירה. gezeira. But אלא חיזר שמך וחזיין מילך. ella
chizer shimcha v’chazyan milach.
Your name is Chizdan and your words are very pleasing." Exactly. So
again, you don’t need to say a פסוק, pasuk, it’s really דרבנן,
derabbanan, but the פסוק pasuk is a nice support, which also fits
into the theme here of quoting פסוקים pesukim as supports for different
pronouncements or advice and so on.
But how do they know it was מדרבנן?
miderabbanan? I mean, like standardly when he quotes a פסוק. pasuk. Well,
first of all, it’s not a פסוק pasuk in the Torah. Yes,
Charlie. Just google it. How did they know it wasn't? What can
I tell you? They knew it wasn’t דאורייתא. de'oraysa. Give me a
break. It’s not like your Torah relates to practice of עטרות חתנים.
ataros chasanim. Anyway, okay. Now תוספות Tosafos by the way of עטרות
חתנים ataros chasanim says פירש בקונטרס עטרה ממש, peirash bekuntres atarah mamash,
it sounds like it was a literal like a type of a
jewelry crown, I mean, something out of like metal or something. ואינו
נראה, v'eino nireh, דאמרינן בפרק קמא דסוטה דלא שנו אלא של ורד
ושל הדס, de'amrinan beperek kama d'Sotah d'lo shanu ella shel vered v'shel
hadas, okay, אבל של קנים ושל חילת מותר, aval shel kanim v'shel
chilas mutar, so they were talking about some type of a, what's
the word for that, a crown made out of a garland, is
that what it is, a wreath?
Yeah, a wreath. Yeah, so something made out of like out of
roses or myrtle or whatever. Okay, but okay. So anyway, the משנה
mishna is like this. Where are we? Back to the גמרא. Gemara.
וחזיין מילך. v'chazyan milach.
רבינא אשכחיה למר בר רב אשי.
Ravina ashkeichei
leMar bar Rav Ashi. רבינא Ravina found מר בר רב אשי Mar
bar Rav Ashi דהוה גדיל כלילא לברתיה. d'hava gadil kelila le'ivratei. He
was growing
a or he was weaving maybe, how do they say that, would
they say it means braiding or weaving? Yeah, braiding a wreath for
his daughter for her wedding. So that’s now an עטרת כלה, ateres
kallah, not a חתנים, chasanim, which also got mentioned in מסכת סוטה.
Masechet Sotah. אמר ליה לא סבר ליה מר הסר המצנפת והרם
העטרה, amar lei lo savar lei mar haser hamitznefet v'hareim ha'atarah, that
if there’s no בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash you can’t have these crowns?
אמר ליה דומיא דכהן גדול בחתני. amar lei dumya d'kohen gadol b'chasanei.
No, no, no, that’s only like by the כהן גדול, kohen gadol,
men can’t wear the crowns, אבל בנשי לא, aval benashi lo, but
not by women.
Which is funny because it was mentioned in the
same משנה, mishna, but yeah, so it’s interesting. Yeah.
So what does he do about that?
I don’t know. He would say that it wouldn’t have fallen into
exactly what the כלה’s kallah case was, right? The גמרא Gemara was
figuring out exactly what the parameters of each one of those was.
Let me see, I don’t think if תוספות Tosafos discusses it, one
minute.
Yeah, if you take a look at תוספות Tosafos he says ודווקא
לחתנים. v'davka lachasanim.
במילוא תוספות עטרות,
bemilu
Tosafos
ataros, ודווקא לחתנים
אסור דומיא דעטרות כלות דמפרש בסוטה דהיא עיר של זהב.
v'davka
lachasanim
assur dumya d'ataros kallos d'mefaresh beSotah dehi ir shel zahav.
Right,
the thing that’s forbidden there is by the כלות kallos is only
like a real like a golden type of a tiara, okay, but
not something like this.
Okay, but that’s just from when they get married, because I know
the גמרא Gemara שבת Shabbos
talks about about עיר של זהב. ir shel zahav. Right, that’s what
תוספות Tosafos refers to. Okay, anyway, so yeah, not
when they get married.
Yeah, yeah, primarily. I mean תוספות Tosafos says that. בפרק במה אשה
לא תצא אשה בעיר של זהב מכלל דבכל שרי, b'perek bameh ishah
lo seitzei ishah b'ir shel zahav miklal dib'chol shari, אלא דווקא חתנים
וכלות אסור. ella davka chasanim v'kallos assur. Exactly, משום שמחה יתירה. mishum
simcha yeseira. Okay, so it’s only when they get married. And anyway,
and it’s a different thing that’s forbidden for the חתן chasan and
the כלה. kallah. The כלה kallah is only really a type of
a metal type of a whatever tiara, something here out of a
wreath is okay for her, so that’s why it was okay for
the כלה. kallah. All right. So now one minute. The גמרא Gemara
now says the following: מאי זאת לא זאת? mai zos lo zos?
What does it mean, this not even this? So דרש רב עוירא
זימנין אמר לה משמיה דרב אמי וזימנין אמר לה משמיה דרב אסי.
darash Rav Avira zimnin amar lah mishmeih d'Rav Ami v'zimnin amar lah
mishmeih d'Rav Assi. Sometimes in the name of רב אמי, Rav Ami,
sometimes in the name of רב אסי. Rav Assi. בשעה שאמר הקדוש
ברוך הוא לישראל, besha'ah she'amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu l'Yisrael, when God said
to ישראל, Yisrael, הסר המצנפת והרם העטרה, haser hamitznefet v'hareim ha'atarah, אמרו
מלאכי השרת לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא. amru malachei hashareis lifnei Hakadosh Baruch
Hu. The angels said to God, ריבונו של עולם, Ribbono shel Olam,
זאת להם לישראל שהקדימו לפניך בסיני נעשה ונשמע? zos lahem l'Yisrael she'hikdimu
lefanecha beSinai na'aseh l'nishma? Which is very evocative of course because the
פסוק pasuk by הר סיני Har Sinai says, right, what is it,
הריין עדיך מעליך? harein adyecha me'alecha?
Right, take your jewelry off from your ויתנצלו בני ישראל את עדים
מהר חורב. vayisnazlu benei Yisrael es adyam me'Har Choreiv.
Right, so they are like removing, and the מדרשים midrashim by הר
סיני Har Sinai is that the מלאכי השרת malachei hashareis came when
they said נעשה ונשמע na'aseh v'nishma and they put on two crowns,
one for נעשה na'aseh and one for נשמע. nishma. And when they
sinned by the עגל, eigel, it says that’s what the פסוק pasuk
means that they had to remove those crowns. So here it’s very
powerful that they’re talking about removing the crowns that they would wear
at the weddings because of חורבן הבית, Churban Habayis, and it’s the
מלאכי השרת malachei hashareis who want to defend keeping the crowns on
because of נעשה ונשמע, na'aseh v'nishma, right? So it’s very much tying
into these מדרשים midrashim and to a פסוק pasuk around the whole
חטא העגל. cheit ha'eigel. So זאת להם לישראל. zos lahem l'Yisrael. ישראל,
Yisrael, this you want to do to the Jewish people who said
לפניך L'fanecha נעשה, Na'aseh, who said נעשה Na'aseh before נשמע? Nishmah? אמר
להם: Amar Lahem: לא זאת אם זאת, Lo Zos Im Zos, זאת,
Zos, לא זאת, Lo Zos, shouldn't this be for ישראל Yisrael ששפילה
את הגבוה והגביהה את השפל she'hishpila es ha'gavoha v'higbiha es ha'shafel that
they brought lowly the high, they brought high the low, meaning they
were like עובדי עבודה זרה? ovdei avodah zarah? They brought down the
glory of the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash והעמידו צלם בהיכל ve'he'emidu tzelem ba'heichal and they
even put a foreign god, an image in the היכל. Heichal. Toby,
you had a question before? No. Okay. Judah, yeah.
Yeah, so they go back and forth between the music and being
silent before your adversaries.
Oh, that's interesting. So
it's two forms of silence.
Yes, it's waiting for השם Hashem to act.
Oh, that's a nice point. Another type of being silent and God
will come. That's very nice. Okay.
Do you think the underlying feeling here is the expectation that the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash would still be rebuilt and the moment that
that type of aspiration shifts then the
inclinations would change and the stringencies would change? So this is like
a learning generation?
Well yeah, but I mean
I do think that it is true that these things are clearly
they were they were dictated right after the חורבן הבית Churban HaBayis
when the sense of loss was the most poignant and pronounced and
I do think that that's the question that we have had a
challenge keeping up the זכר לחורבן zeicher l'churban practices as it gets
further and further away. I mean so like how many people like
the whole thing about the the music? I mean now again we
have more recorded music than live music but how many people leave
the section of their house unplastered זכר לחורבן? zeicher l'churban? So you're
right, I mean in the immediate aftermath this is obviously much more
powerful and poignant. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay.
דרש רב עוירא Darash Rav Avira same דרשה, drasha, same person giving
the דרשה drasha in the name of the same one or two
people. מזמנין אמרי לה משמיה דרב אמי ומזמנין אמרי לה משמיה דרב
אסי. mizmanin amri lah mishmei d'Rav Ami u'mizmanin amri lah mishmei d'Rav
Assi. Sometimes in the name of רב אמי Rav Ami sometimes רב
אסי. Rav Assi. מאי דכתיב mai de'chsiv what is meant by the
verse כה אמר ה' אם שלמים וכן רבים וכן נגוזו ועבר? Koh
amar Hashem im shleimim v'chen rabbim v'chen nagozu v'avar? If complete ones
and many and many, so it has been sort of cut off
and passed away. What does that mean? So אם רואה אדם שמזונותיו
מצומצמין im ro'eh adam she'mezonosav mtzumtzamin if a person sees that his
livelihood is his food is very limited, he's only making scraping by
a living, so יעשה מהן צדקה, ya'aseh mehen tzedakah, he should give
צדקה. tzedakah. So where do we see that? וכל שכן שהם מרובים.
v'chol sheken sheheim mrubim. So שלמים shleimim somehow means like it's complete
but it's like bare, it's
just it's not excessive. I don't know how שלמים shleimim means that
it's limited. But anyway צדקה tzedakah we'll see is from the word
נגוזו. nagozu. And certainly if he has a lot of money he
should give צדקה. tzedakah. מאי mai and I don't anyway I don't
get how they get מצומצמין mtzumtzamin from מזונותיו. mezonosav. I don't know.
Anyway מאי וכן נגוזו ועבר? mai v'chen nagozu v'avar? תנא דבי רבי
ישמעאל: Tana d'vei Rabbi Yishmael: כל הגוזז מנכסיו kol ha'gozez mi'nechasav anybody
who shears your
property, so that's נגוזו, nagozu, ועושה מהן צדקה v'oseh mehen tzedakah and
you give it and you do charity with it, ניצל מדינה של
גיהנום nitzal mi'dinah shel Gehennom is saved from the judgment of גיהנום
Gehennom ועבר v'avar and you'll be able to pass through as we'll
see in a minute. Okay. תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל: Tana d'vei Rabbi
Yishmael: כל הגוזז מנכסיו ועושה מהן צדקה kol ha'gozez mi'nechasav v'oseh mehen
tzedakah anybody who shears it and does צדקה, tzedakah, ניצל מדינה של
גיהנום. nitzal mi'dinah shel Gehennom. משל לשתי רחלות mashal l'shtei recheilos or
it's a parable to two sheep, lambs, שהיו עוברות במים she'hayu ovros
ba'mayim they were passing through the water. אחת גזוזה ואחת אינה גזוזה
achas gzuzah v'achas einah gzuzah one is sheared and one is not
sheared. גזוזה עברה ושאינה גזוזה לא עברה gzuzah avrah v'she'einah gzuzah lo
avrah the one that's sheared is able to pass through, it doesn't
get weighed down, the water doesn't get trapped in the wool and
it pulls it down, and the other one cannot get through. Okay.
Okay,
let's take a look.
Yeah. Okay.
ועניתיך v'iniisicha so that's I think the end of the פסוק, pasuk,
right? No, is that a different פסוק? pasuk? No, the end of
the פסוק. pasuk. Okay. So what's ועניתיך? v'iniisicha? אמר מר זוטרא: amar
Mar Zutra: אפילו עני המתפרנס מן הצדקה afilu ani ha'misparnes min ha'tzedakah
even if a poor person who is getting who is himself receiving
צדקה tzedakah to put food on the table יעשה צדקה ya'aseh tzedakah
that even such a person should give צדקה, tzedakah, should recognize the
gift of their money and to be able to give it to
others as well, maybe others that are even less fortunate than themselves.
Okay. לא אענך עוד lo a'aneich od I will no longer afflict
you. תנא רב יוסף: tana Rav Yosef: שוב אין מראין לו סימני
עניות. shuv ein marin lo simanei aniyus. So over here from the
word of עוני oni if even if a poor person gives צדקה
tzedakah they will no longer see any more signs of poverty. Okay.
And with that we end a whole long passage of אגדתא Aggadeta
that came from showing that רב יוסף Rav Yosef was somebody you
could trust, and the idea of saying בפני נכתב bifnei nichtav not
having to say it when you come from בבל Bavel to חוץ
לארץ chutz la'aretz and vice versa. Now we turn to the discussion
of the boundaries of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. And as I've been
saying from the beginning and תוספות Tosafos has a long תוספות Tosafos
to discuss earlier, same as it came up about בבל, Bavel, how
much are we dealing with standard boundaries borders that we use elsewhere
like in laws of תרומות ומעשרות Trumos u'Ma'asros and how much are
we drawing specific borders that are specific to the concerns of בפני
נכתב? bifnei nichtav? בפני נכתב Bifnai Nichtav about saying לשמה Lishmah and
being able to establish the signatures? So the גמרא Gemara has seemed
to be it's much more tailor-made and it's specific to the concerns
here, but let's take a look at this גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so
רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer מרקם למזרח, me-Rekem le-mizrach, from Rekem
to mizrach, and Rekem is in the east, and from עכו Akko
to the north, and אשקלון Ashkelon in the south. Those are the
north the edge points of the land of Israel for these purposes.
So the גמרא Gemara says למימרא דעכו לצפונה של ארץ ישראל קיימא
le-meimra de-Akko li-tzfonah shel Eretz Yisrael kaima that Akko is to the
north of
Israel. ורמינהי Ur'minhu on this: היה מהלך מעכו לכזיב, haya mehalech me-Akko
le-Kziv, somebody is going from Akko to Kziv, and Kziv is further
north. מימינו למזרח הדרך טמאה משום ארץ העמים. Mi-yemino le-mizrach ha-derech tmeiah
mishum Eretz ha-Amim. To his right, that's how you know he's going
north, right? He's going from Akko, okay, here's Akko, here's Kziv, so
it says to his right, here's your walking, the guy's walking, okay,
okay, so to his right, his right is this way, and that's
the east, right? So you know that he's walking north. Okay, he's
going from Akko to Kziv, מימינו למזרח mi-yemino le-mizrach to his right
on the east,
okay, הדרך טמאה משום ארץ העמים. ha-derech tmeiah mishum Eretz ha-Amim. That's
considered ארץ העמים, Eretz ha-Amim, that's חוץ לארץ, Chutz la-Aretz, okay, on
his right.
Even though בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael we're not
yeah well we're not worrying about what happened in the time of
יהושע. Yehoshua. This is about קדושת ארץ ישראל Kedushas Eretz Yisrael in
the time of the second of the, you know, when they had
the טומאת ארץ העמים, tumas Eretz ha-Amim, so again, this is also
not about הלכות גיטין, hilchos Gittin, okay, but this is presumably where
they settled in the time of the second בית המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash
exactly what stage in the time of the second בית המקדש. Beis
ha-Mikdash. Okay, ופטורה מן המעשר ומן השביעית. u-pturah min ha-ma'aser u-min ha-shvi'is.
It's exempt from מעשר ma'aser and שביעית, shvi'is, so it's about it
doesn't have קדושת ארץ Kedushas Aretz at least at least second בית
המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash period, okay, or after that. עד שיודע לך שהיא
חייבת Ad she-yivada lcha she-hi chayaves until you know that there's an
area that maybe was included, okay. This is the path, okay, is
it just the border of the land of Israel is exactly on
the path from Akko to Kziv, so for the most part that's
חוץ לארץ. Chutz la-Aretz. If you find out oh actually there's a
little section over here that's part of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, fine,
so that section is part of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael if you
find out find it out. But as a rule the border is
defined by that path, okay. עד שיודע לך שהיא חייבת. Ad she-yivada
lcha she-hi chayaves. משמאלו למערב הדרך טהורה משום ארץ העמים. Mismolo le-ma'arav
ha-derech tehorah mishum Eretz ha-Amim. So the left westward it's טהורה, tehorah,
it's the land of Israel וחייבת במעשר ובשביעית, ve-chayaves be-ma'aser u-ve-shvi'is, חייבת
במעשר chayaves be-ma'aser and שביעית shvi'is עד שיודע לך שהיא פטורה ad
she-yivada lcha she-hi pturah unless you find out that for some reason
it's exempt, okay. So here you have how
would it be exempt?
Well, are these exactly on the border of Israel?
Akko is on the ocean,
is Akko on the Mediterranean Sea?
And and the thing is there's
no land there's no I mean it's literally on the sea.
Historically Akko
actually stuck out into the sea.
Towards the right, at least in the תנ"ך, Tanach, towards the right
is מזרח mizrach I I thought.
No but it's saying you're walking,
it
says you're walking הולך מעכו לכזיב. holech me-Akko le-Kziv.
I understand the problem I don't I don't so I don't understand.
Well it's describing it's
normally like our orientation on a map.
Where's אכזיב? Achziv?
To the north.
I understand that.
But towards the right.
Look look everybody look look talk to Rabbi Google. Here's Akko, right,
and here's אכזיב, Achziv, right? Everybody see this? Here's the path. Okay,
there is there is no, but first there's land to the left
of the path. The path isn't on the water. The border the
shore is here. Okay. So you're walking from Akko to Kziv, okay,
there is land here.
Who cares, but there's land.
That's the point, right? That's the point. So this side is חוץ
לארץ, Chutz la-Aretz, this side is ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, the land
between the path and the sea is ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, unless
you know that for some reason maybe a little section is חוץ
לארץ, Chutz la-Aretz, okay.
Everybody see the picture? Don't give me a hard time. All right,
so
there you go, doubting the גמרא Gemara I can't believe you. Okay
anyway, all right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
Okay. משמאלו למערב הדרך טהורה משום ארץ העמים וחייבת במעשר ובשביעית עד
שיודע לך שהיא פטורה. Mismolo le-ma'arav ha-derech tehorah mishum Eretz ha-Amim ve-chayaves
be-ma'aser u-ve-shvi'is ad she-yivada lcha she-hi pturah. עד היכן? Ad heichan? Until
far? עד כזיב, ad Kziv,
which seems a little redundant. Okay but presumably means that after Kziv,
that's the very northernmost tip of Israel. It doesn't go beyond that.
רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yishmael be-Rabbi Yossi omer, רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael the son of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says משום אביו
mishum aviv in the name of his father רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi,
עד לבלבו. ad Lavlavo. It even goes further than Kziv, it even
goes to Lavlavo. Okay. ואמר אביי Ve-amar Abaye and I don't know
where Lavlavo is. אמר אביי Amar Abaye רצועה נפקא retzu'ah nafka like
a small strip goes out. So if you take a look,
ורש"י ve-Rashi has a little picture. Okay because what does that
mean that
no, I'm sorry. No no no I'm sorry so that's already the
answer. So the question is you see that Kziv is the north,
so why does our גמרא Gemara say that... עכו Akko is the
north, you know, for the land of ישראל. Yisrael. Now, by the
way, before we get to the answer, you see that the simple
answer would have been, since when should we assume that the boundaries
of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for the הלכות halachos of גיטין Gittin
and בפני נחתם Befanay Nechtam are the same as they are for
טומאת ארץ העמים Tumas Eretz Ha'Amim and for תרומות ומעשרות? Terumos u'Ma'asros?
Okay, and here you see that the גמרא Gemara at least this
גמרא Gemara as opposed to like earlier discussions seems to feel like
no, we're going to assume either one of two things. Either we're
going to assume that we're not making a special definition for the
laws of גיטין, Gittin, we're just going to use a standard definition,
okay, that's one possibility. The other possibility is that we're going to
assume that the same place which was settled
and has קדושת ארץ ישראל Kedushas Eretz Yisrael and has תרומות ומעשרות
Terumos u'Ma'asros we will assume unless we know otherwise that they overlap.
Meaning we're not saying that they are the same definition, but we're
going to assume that they overlap unless we know otherwise. Anyway, the
גמרא Gemara says that if for laws of תרומות ומעשרות Terumos u'Ma'asros
this is the north, how come we're saying that this is the
north? And the גמרא's Gemara's answer is,
רצועה נפקא, retzu'ah nafka, it's only a little bit of a strip,
which means that basic ישראל Yisrael ends here, okay? The basic you
know real land here. There's a tiny little strip of
ישראל, Yisrael, this tiny little strip that goes like this, that we're
not going to bother to talk about when we talk about the
most northern thing. It's a little strip that remains. I mean it's
true all of you are telling me this is right on the
border, so there's very little left of ישראל Yisrael from here to
here, it's just that little strip by the border. So that we're
not going to talk about. The real עיקר יישוב ikkar yishuv ends
here. But we're not denying that this is also part of ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael but if you would say ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
goes up to כזיב, Keziv, you'd assume it meant that you've got
a major part of the land until כזיב. Keziv. That's not true.
The major part of the land is till עכו Akko and there's
a little strip that remains going all the way up to כזיב.
Keziv. Okay?
רצועה נפקא, retzu'ah nafka, little strip goes. So the גמרא Gemara says,
ואי תנא סימנא הכא? ve-ay tana siman hacha? So big deal, so
for a little strip you're going to give all of that, you're
going to write a whole משנה Mishnah to
describe that little strip of land whether it's חייב chayav in תרומות
ומעשרות Terumos u'Ma'asros which is a funny question like why not? That's
הלכה, halachah, we want to know whether you have to give תרומות
ומעשרות Terumos u'Ma'asros from the area between עכו Akko and כזיב. Keziv.
But anyway that's the גמרא's Gemara's question, so let's see what the
גמרא's Gemara's answer is.
But תוספות Tosafos take a look at תוספות, Tosafos, well let's first
stop and see תוספות. Tosafos. תוספות Tosafos says, פירוש בקונטרס ומי חשיבא
חדא רצועה, perush bekuntress umi hashiva chada retzu'ah, just for that little
strip is it so important לאנוחי בה סימנא, le'anochei bah simana, to
give exactly these exact parameters? So תוספות Tosafos says, וקשה וכי אין
לתנא לציין גבולי ארץ ישראל? ve-kasheh ve-chi ein letana letsayen gevulei Eretz
Yisrael? I don't understand, of course it's relevant, we want to know
if you're חייב chayav תרומות ומעשרות Terumos u'Ma'asros in that strip or
not. Okay, ועוד מה ראיה מעשר רב פפא ve'od mah ra'ayah Ma'aser
Rav Pappa etc. etc. Okay,
the גמרא Gemara says, so if you look a little bit, he
says מפרשים אינהו שמואל, mefarshim innu Shmuel, so few lines down, דלאו
אשינויא פריך, d'lav ahinuya pareich, it's not a question on the answer
that it's just a strip. אלא ברייתא דקתני למזרח ולמערב הדרך וכי
דבר מועט כמו דרך שייך למימר בו מזרח ומערב? ella beraisa de-sani
lemizrach u'le'maarav haderech ve-chi davar muer kemo derech shayach lemeimar bo mizrach
u'maarav? תוספות Tosafos doesn't say that the question is why are you
discussing this area and telling me that this area is ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, it's saying that
normally a little path like you're going to say that the path
defines the border? That's a little trivial of a marker to be
defining a border. All right.
Did we have the swamp by the second pond?
I was wondering the same thing. Anyway one way or another let's
see what the גמרא's Gemara's answer is. So why are you bothering
to describe either use that path as a border or describe the
הלכה halachah of that little strip? So the גמרא Gemara says, אין
קרא נמי הוי סימנא, in kura nami havi simana,
yes even a פסוק pasuk uses descriptions like that, דכתיב ויאמרו הנה
חג ה' בשילה מימים ימימה אשר מצפונה לבית אל
מזרחה השמש למסילה העולה מבית אל שכמה ומנגב ללבונה. de-chsiv vayomru hinei
chag Hashem beShilo miyamim yamima asher mitspona leBeis El mizrecha hashemesh
limsila ha'olah miBeis El Shechema uminegev leLevona. So there according to תוספות
Tosafos
you see it's even giving directions vis-a-vis orientation vis-a-vis a path. Okay,
ואמר רב פפא למזרחה של מסילה, ve'amar Rav Pappa lemizrachah shel mesilah,
it means to the east of the path. The path is the
marker. So you see that you use even a path as a
marker. Okay anyway what we have is the basic major עיקר יישוב
ikkar yishuv of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael stops at עכו, Akko, a
little path that remains between עכו Akko and כזיב. Keziv. But again
interesting the most relevant thing is that we're using as a point
of reference the הלכות halachos of תרומות ומעשרות Terumos u'Ma'asros and now
we're going to continue to see how much does that become our
definition in this סוגיא. sugya. Basically the point is in some of
the סוגיות sugyos in the first פרק perek the parameters are very
tailor made to the concerns of גט get and in some like
the סוגיא sugya we're in right now it seems to be following
standard definitions of תרומות ומעשרות. Terumos u'Ma'asros. Okay and the סוגיות sugyos
don't seem to be talking to one another. So let's take a
look.
Okay. תנא
חדא tana chada we have one ברייתא beraisa that teaches המביא גט
בספינה כמביא בארץ ישראל. hameivi get besfina kemevi b'Eretz Yisrael. If you're
bringing a גט get in a boat it's like bringing it in
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Get a boat you're bringing in a boat,
it's like you're bringing in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. ותניא אידך, כמביא
בחוץ לארץ. V'tanya idach k'mavi b'chutz la'aretz,
You're in, you're in the ספינה sfina that's on the, you're here
you are, you're in your boat, okay, and you've and you actually
before you don't get off of the boat. You actually have the
wife come onto the boat, okay, and you deliver it in the
boat and you have not you have not de- what is it?
Disembarked. Okay, so you're in international waters. Okay. Are you bringing it
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or are you bringing it in חוץ
לארץ? Chutz La'aretz? Okay, so what? You're at the port? Yeah. Okay.
So I guess well I guess the question about I mean or
maybe it was written on the boat, maybe it was a sailor
who was on the boat. I don't know what it was. Anyway,
are you in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or are you in חוץ
לארץ Chutz La'aretz when you're on the boat? Okay.
So, if you look at רש״י, Rashi, המביא גט בספינה, Hamavee get
bi'sfina, שנכתב בספינה, she'nichtav bi'sfina, וקסבר דבנהרות דארץ ישראל קאמר. v'kasavar d'binaharos
d'Eretz Yisrael ka'amar. Or he actually had you in the Mediterranean. He
has it in one of the rivers. Okay. כמביא בארץ ישראל, k'mavi
b'Eretz Yisrael, כאילו מביא דרך יבשה ואין צריך לומר בפני נכתב.
k'ilu mivi derech
yavasha
v'ein tzarich lomar bifanay nichtav. יבשה. Yavasha. יבשה. Yavasha. Thank you. ותניא
אידך כמביא בחוץ לארץ, v'tanya idach k'mavi b'chutz la'aretz. שהנהר אינו תור
יבשה לכל תורת הארץ.
she'hanahar eino tor
yavasha l'chol toras ha'aretz. Okay, so the question is actually
so forget this. I gave I already gave a different a more
complicated thing. You are here on some river, okay? You're in some
river and you're in some boat and you're giving a גט get
in a boat in a river. Okay, are you in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and you don't have to say? Or the rivers are
not counted as part of ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? If you're in
the river, you're not on the land. You're not in the land
of Israel, so it's like you're in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz so
you have to say בפני נכתב. bifanay nichtav. Okay. So what's the
הלכה? halacha? So well let's well we'll take a look. If you
think that it follows the laws of תרומות ומעשרות, trumos and ma'asros,
it might matter if you're on dirt or not, right? So this
shows you how far we're going to go by focusing on the
תרומות ומעשרות trumos and ma'asros as the model. Okay, so המביא גט
בספינה כמביא בארץ ישראל Hamavee get bi'sfina k'mavi b'Eretz Yisrael ותניא אידך
V'tanya idach, כמביא בחוץ לארץ. k'mavi b'chutz la'aretz. אמר רבי ירמיה לא
קשיא. Amar Rabbi Yirmiya lo kashya. הא רבי יהודה הא רבנן. Ha
Rabbi Yehuda ha Rabbanan. It's the הא רבי יהודה הא רבנן Ha
Rabbi Yehuda ha Rabbanan and now it seems to get a little
bit wild. So דתנן ditnan we taught in the משנה: mishna: עפר
חוץ לארץ הבא בספינה לארץ. Afar chutz la'aretz haba bi'sfina l'aretz.
You have dirt from חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz that's on the boat
and the boat is in the ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. It's in
let's say רש״י Rashi says it's in some river, okay? So what?
What river? There are no rivers in Israel?
You mean he's in the Jordan? You mean it's like three feet
wide or whatever?
Let's say, yeah well we're going to actually see, okay?
So you have stuff growing on the dirt in the boat and
the dirt in the boat is the hull of the boat, okay?
So you've got your... we'll take it out of the air, we'll
put them by the Jordan. Anyway, you've got here, you've got your
boat, okay, and you've got some dirt in the boat and you've
got something growing from your dirt in your boat, okay, and your
boat is in some river in Israel. Okay.
All right. There's your boat in some river in Israel, okay, make
a... all right. Now is that, is the stuff that grows there,
is that growing in the land of Israel or not? Is it
חייב במעשר
ובשביעית? chayiv b'ma'aser u'v'shevi'is? עפר חוץ לארץ הבא בספינה לארץ חייב במעשר
ובשביעית. Afar chutz la'aretz haba bi'sfina l'aretz chayiv b'ma'aser u'v'shevi'is. אמר רבי
יהודה אימתי בזמן שהספינה גוששת, Amar Rabbi Yehuda emasy b'zman she'hasfina gosheshes,
if the boat is like sort of scraping the bottom
of the riverbed.
Okay, because then it's like connected to the dirt on the bottom
of the river and then it's connected to the dirt of ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. או אין הספינה גוששת פטור. O ein hasfina gosheshes
patur. Okay so now what we are going to assume is, okay
that basically you're in a boat which is which is in the
river so according to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma you are in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael the same way dirt would be in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael and would be stuff would be חייב chayiv in
תרומות ומעשרות trumos and ma'asros and according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
if the boat isn't scraping the bottom of the riverbed you're not
in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Now of course the funny thing about
all of this is that that's a debate of whether you say
the stuff grew from dirt of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. It's a
תרומות ומעשרות trumos and ma'asros debate. How is this relevant to a
גט get discussion? So it seems very clear that what we're just
doing is we're just borrowing an existing
definition from תרומות ומעשרות trumos and ma'asros and applying it to גט
get even though it's really completely irrelevant but like all right but
you gotta define what's in and what's out and we'll use this
as a definition. Still though even if you're just going to use
a prepackaged definition what does it have to do with the fact
whether the dirt is the dirt and whether it's anchored on the
bottom or not anchored on the bottom? Like you can't even translate
that debate.
But anyway actually you say בפני bifanay if you're worried about...
no that clearly that was my point though that it's obviously not
based on the substance of the concerns but even as a formal
just take a prepackaged definition how do you apply questions of like
whether the boat that relates to where the dirt is? Okay but
anyway let's we'll read a little bit more if I have a
second we'll read a line from תוספות. Tosafot. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: הכא במאי עסקינן? Hacha b'mai askinan? No so that's
what the גמרא Gemara says let's say this is the debate. אביי
אמר Abaye amar הוי הא רבי יהודה. hava ha Rabbi Yehuda. No
it's both רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda he... לא קשיא כאן בזמן שאינו
ספינה גוששת כאן בזמן שספינה גוששת. Lo kashya kahn bizman she'eino sefina
gosheshes kahn bizman shesefina gosheshes. It depends if the boat is scraping
the bottom or not. If it's scraping the bottom, it's like you're
in the, you're on the land of Israel. If it's not scraping
the bottom, it's not like you're in the land of Israel.
Okay. אמר רבי זירא עציץ נקוב המונח על גבי יתדות פלוגתא דרבי
יהודה ורבנן. amar Rabbi Zeira Atzitz nakuv hamunach al gabei yetedos palugta
de'Rabbi Yehuda ve'Rabbanan. Now we're sort of a little bit digressing and
he's saying, let's say you've got here not on the river, on
land, you've got a little flower pot, okay? עציץ נקוב. Atzitz nakuv.
And it's got a hole in the bottom and it's got something
growing out of it, okay, and it's suspended off the ground. And
this is the ground, okay? So if you've got a flower pot,
if it's connected to the ground
and it's got something growing out of it and it's got a
hole in the bottom, then this is all just seen like a
big lump in the ground, right? The hole here in the bottom
means that it's not completely, right, there's a part of the ground
that's connected, so this is just a big lump in the ground
and it's growing. But here there's air space between it. So he
says that's the same issue here because you've got dirt, okay, you've
got a boat, maybe we consider the boat like an עציץ נקוב,
Atzitz nakuv, maybe it's somewhat porous or something, although I'll read you
רש"י Rashi in a second, okay, and you've got, okay, right, well
it doesn't actually have a hole, okay, so somehow it's not considered
like this but it's considered enough like this that that's the debate,
okay, about whether that's considered enough connected. רבנן. Rabbanan. אמר רבא דילמא
לא היא עד כאן לא קאמר רבי יהודה התם אלא בספינה העשויה
לברוח. Amar Rava dilma lo hi ad kahn lo ka'amar Rabbi Yehuda
hasam ela be'sefina ha'asuya livroach. No, maybe you can make a distinction.
That's only by a boat, a boat normally moves, so it's never
really considered in its place and therefore that's why the רבנן Rabbanan
say it's not considered part of Israel, that's why רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says unless it's, oh because I'm sorry I misquoted, because remember
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said when it's scraping the bottom it is
part of Israel, when it's not it's not. But the רבנן Rabbanan
said it's always part of Israel, right? Right, the רבנן Rabbanan said
it's always part. So the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and
the רבנן Rabbanan when it's touching the bottom, that's like this case.
Okay, we're assuming the bottom of the boat is considered porous, it
is like it has a hole. Okay, so when it's touching the
bottom everybody agrees, but when it's not touching the bottom that's the
debate. So the גמרא Gemara says oh well it's not touching the
bottom, that's this case. Okay, so it's the same case because the
רבנן Rabbanan and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda debate when there's dirt in
the boat and it's not touching the bottom. So the גמרא Gemara
says maybe it's לא
היא. lo hi. עד כאן לא קאמר רבי יהודה התם, Ad kahn
lo ka'amar Rabbi Yehuda hasam, there רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said why
when it's not touching the bottom is it not dirt in the
land of Israel? אלא בספינה העשויה לברוח, Ela be'sefina ha'asuya livroach, because
a boat normally moves, it's not going to stay around. אבל עציץ
שאינו עשוי לברוח לא, Aval atzitz she'eino asui livroach lo, but by
the flower pot, if it stays in its place he would say
that it is part of Israel. אי נמי, ee nami, or also
you could say, עד כאן לא קאמרי רבנן התם אלא בספינה דלא
מפסקי אוירא דמיא דארעא סמיכתא דמיא. ad kahn lo ka'amri Rabbanan hasam
ela be'sefina de'lo mafseki avira demaya de'ar'a semichta damya. Why do the
רבנן Rabbanan say it? Because the רבנן Rabbanan say there's not air,
okay, there's water, but water could be seen as like thicker ground.
It's still the stuff that sits, you know, that's there, that's part
of the, that's part of the seafloor. Okay, so in that case
they could say that that's considered connected to the ground even if
it's not touching the ground. It's like thick ground.
ואילו עציץ דמפסק אוירא לא, Ve'ilu atzitz demfask avira lo, but a
flower pot where there's actual air, then they would not say it.
Anyway, that's all very interesting in terms of the debate of תרומות
ומעשרות, Terumos u'ma'asros, but the irony still is that they're going ahead
and using that debate for the issue about the גט. get. So
we'll just take a look at one second in תוספות Tosfos about
this, what this is all about, okay? So if you take a
look at תוספות, Tosfos, two תוספות, Tosfos, first of all תוספות Tosfos
says, I guess I have to read you this one line of
תוספות Tosfos of the עציץ נקוב, atzitz nakuv, how that could be
considered the comparison, okay? So רש"י Rashi says the following, עציץ נקוב
פירש בקונטרס דספינה דלעיל של חרס ואינה צריכה לינקב. Atzitz nakuv peirash
bakuntres de'sefina deleil shel cheres ve'einah tzricha lenakev.
The boat is made out of pottery, I don't know how far
you're going to get with boats out of pottery, and therefore it
doesn't need a hole to be considered porous. אע"ג דהשתא מונחת בקרקע
ולאו במיא. af al gav de'hashta munachas be'karka ve'lav bemaya. Okay, and
then he goes on and on about that, about the question about
why the boat is similar. But then the end of this תוספות
Tosfos he says like this, he says, he says basically what sense
does this whole comparison make? And I just want to read you
the one punchline of תוספות, Tosfos, he says like this.
You know what, let's not because it's already 8:30 so we'll just,
yeah, we'll pick up tomorrow. I just want to read you kind
of how to deal with this bizarre comparison, we will pick up
with that point tomorrow, okay, so we'll end here for now.